[SPEAKER_01]: In the suttas it says that to see pleasant feeling as painful, which you just discussed in detail right now, but then it goes on to say painful feeling as a dart and neutral feeling as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So why not just painful feeling as painful?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the aspect of seeing it as a dart?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, pleasant feeling as unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the first one, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: See pleasure as displeasure, displeasure as a dot, a neutral feeling as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why would that be there?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why do you need to say
[SPEAKER_02]: The prospect of an unpleasant feeling should be seen as a doubt, should be seen as even worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it's double painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, that's kind of what you're trying to see, to convey.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Whom are you conveying it to?
[SPEAKER_02]: Who are you seeing it for?
[SPEAKER_02]: For whom are you rewriting the context of pleasant, unpleasant, neutral?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, obviously for the mind, like for the animal, but I would say more like experientially actually for the tendency.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is what the animal is for you there and then, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so that's the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's to regard it so that the animal will turn away from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to, say, regard it twice as much.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, see, like, say... and actually that's probably something people can relate to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, oh, I can handle a moderate amount of, say, sensual engagement.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or acting out of ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can handle it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can handle what comes after.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know it's going to be uncomfortable, but I can handle it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That means the animal will remain bound by those feelings, by ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Won't be tamed.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you are practicing regarding of, say, unpleasant feeling, prospect of an unpleasant feeling, as a dart,
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you're increasing the value of woe.
[SPEAKER_02]: You shouldn't be handling it to begin with, because it's a trap.
[SPEAKER_02]: It carries the danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I can handle a little bit of poison.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: A gram of poison or a full glass, it's equally deadly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the perception you need to develop, so that the animal completely turns away, because anything less than that won't be freedom.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're regarding the pain as twice as bad, so that things... so that when things are not painful, the animal won't get careless.
[SPEAKER_02]: There'll be enough left in the bank of that context to keep you on the right track.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, it's because the usual tendency towards painful feeling is to either say, look, I can handle it, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just like, no, you can't handle it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know how painful it will be, one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: As well with the dart, you might say, you don't know who's shooting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He might shoot it with incredible strength and it just goes through you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, all of the circumstantial implications.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the point is that this whole practice of regarding is like should apply to even the mere possibility of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're not just waiting.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to be waiting for the pain to regard it as as an arrow.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just the mere prospect of things turning painful, if regarded as a dart, as an arrow,
[SPEAKER_02]: Means mind won't be careless in regard to things that are not painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you're, as I said, you're inflating, you're increasing the value of staying on the right track, because otherwise you won't.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it were not necessary to be done, the Buddha wouldn't have said do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, again, it's not like on the level of you need to say irrationally stuff, everything is horrible, everything is bad.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it's just a mere prospect of being touched by pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: If the mind is not fully trained, you should regard it... No, actually, I should...
[SPEAKER_02]: I should not be in that position, because that would be a dart, that would be a deadly arrow.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what do you do now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, now, because of that,
[SPEAKER_02]: When the choice of sensuality presents itself, I say no, to protect myself from the possible deadly arrow.
[SPEAKER_02]: When the choice of ill will presents itself, I say no, again, to protect myself from the deadly arrow.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I will be giving zero intentional basis for the deadly arrow to land on me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, actually, developing that perception feeds into the first one as well, seeing... Yeah, yeah, of course, of course, of course, yeah, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then the pleasant feeling will be seen cautiously, seen as, well, this is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I have to be cautious because it might be a trap, that's already an unpleasant experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, impermanence for neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: The possibility of neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: To see that as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just when painful feeling is present.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, see, the possibility of a neutral feeling would be like the subtlest form of feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, obviously, the possibility of discomfort, it's already uncomfortable on some level.
[SPEAKER_02]: The possibility of pleasure, that you still are deeming valuable, it's kind of felt elating, pleasant on some level.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the possibility of a neutral feeling is already neutral.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you regard that as impermanent, as unownable,
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, there's nothing else for you to worry about.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the thing is, it's not a practice that you could just start in the middle of everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the result.
[SPEAKER_02]: The result of training rightly in regard to the pleasant feelings, not falling for its hooks and pressures.
[SPEAKER_02]: The result of training rightly in the unpleasant feeling, not losing sight and context and becoming negligent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you get to discern the neutrality, the feelings that, basically, in order to discern a neutral feeling, as the Sutta says, you need to have developed some wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, it's just not seen, so it's always going to be, basically, unpleasant and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the wisdom is developed on account of training rightly in regard to the pleasure and displeasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's kind of the subtlest part whereby, say, you have already... the mind is already, to a great degree, tamed, contained through the right context, regards pleasure as a trap.
[SPEAKER_02]: Uncomfortable regards pain as twice as painful, because if you lose the sight, again, the suffering will increase and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, yeah, say you're developed in all of that, you could be on the level of, oh, neither pleasure nor displeasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I regard that as, as I said, a reason on its own, impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Its manifestation is the reason for its ending, is the reason for its impermanence, even if it still endures here.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to see it go away.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in other words, there will be no asavas left anywhere to hide in regard to this attitude towards pleasure, or that attitude towards pain, or the attitude towards the neutral feeling that's kind of not seeing it to the extent, turning away, looking past it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you train rightly in regard to the pleasure, you are training rightly in regard to the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're training rightly in regard to the neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you train rightly in regard to the pain, you're training rightly in regard to the other two.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's it's like different facets of the same principle of training, that as you train in it, even more of it becomes discernible.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even subtler aspects of it become more and more discernible, because, as I said, you are actually training in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, when you say you are in a state of neither pleasure nor displeasure, just like sitting in your kuti, for example, and you could say things are neutral, objectively neutral,
[SPEAKER_02]: Where is that feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Are you feeling it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you feel it like, oh, I am feeling this?
[SPEAKER_02]: Are you in it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is it in you?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or... What's your relationship with the neutrality of that feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: I would say the usual tendency is to go for, I'm feeling it, rather than it's arisen by itself or on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So actually not seeing that aspect of uncontrollability,
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's the perception you could be developing then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's... See, the point is, it's not like you need to contrive or imagine a neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is, you need to build it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: You build it up through not pursuing pleasant feelings and not denying, resisting the unpleasant feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: You build it up by rightly training in regard to those palpable feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, in solitude and so on, when you're left with neutral feeling, again, that's where you could start now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, I could see this thing as there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the... being felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not necessarily see myself feeling it, or in it, or comes from me, and relate myself personally to it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: And yeah, I mean, those perceptions are doable, but... And people can, as I said, even wrap their head around even... even before they're able to do them, and then think they're doing them, because they make sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what I'm saying is, you don't want to be doing it on the basis of an imaginary neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to actually be feeling a neutral, neither pleasant nor unpleasant, and then seeing that thing real as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not coming from me, not in relation to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just there, first and foremost.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then I choose to relate to this or this or that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But first and foremost, it's just felt enduring on its own.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not trying to change it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not trying to understand it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not trying to get into it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm just trying to see it for what it is, while it's there, to the extent that it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And see, that's already, like, what we spoke before, that whole development of, like, peripheral awareness of indirectly attending.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you can't directly attend, well, actually, to any of your feelings, to be...
[SPEAKER_02]: But when it comes to the neutral feeling, a reason on its own, on account of rightly training in regard to the pleasant and unpleasant feeling, through right virtue, right restraint, and so on, that feeling is even subtler, peripherally.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're expecting to see it as a thing that can be directly attended and measured through your perception, you know when you're seeing it correctly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will be imagining it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's like you don't force it or rush it as to, okay, I must present these perceptions in regard to neutral feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Are things neither pleasant or unpleasant now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me learn how to discern that as something that's already being felt while I'm discerning it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you want to feel it, but you don't want to be doing the feeling, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's already felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you want to discern that which is already felt as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not like, oh, I want to feel it as such because that's what I learned.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why, again, the whole training in virtue and guarding of the senses has to be developed beforehand, because if those coarse modes of interfering are not tamed and subdued, you're not going to be able to stay on the level of not forcing the feeling of that which is already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'll be doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'll be falling for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you know,
[SPEAKER_02]: You look back, step back, look at the entirety of your current enduring situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's felt pleasantly, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not trying to change it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's felt unpleasant, you're not trying...
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's felt neither pleasant or unpleasant, you're not trying to change that either.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's the first and foremost, say, training for somebody that is living according to the virtues, celibacy and guarding of the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's like, let me peripherally not lose the sight of an enduring feeling,
[SPEAKER_02]: For as long as it endures, really.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it doesn't matter why or how it came about.
[SPEAKER_02]: So don't fall into rationalizing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, it's because it doesn't really matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's completely irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as a matter of fact, yeah, the suttas even say that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, the feelings can be born out of, what, seven, eight reasons.
[SPEAKER_02]: Change of the elements, earth, water, fire, air.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then one of them is like circumstance, accident.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then another one is previous karma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either way, feeling is there and the training is the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, no matter why.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's another way of staying with the feeling correctly, would be, say, you're building up the right environment, right restraint, your inseclusion, and, like, I don't know, feeling of displeasure is present.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you see your mind wanting to rationalize and explain it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's like, oh, I'll actually...
[SPEAKER_02]: I won't fuel that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Although, if it feels like it will offer a solution, no, I'm not actually fighting for this reason why the feelings came about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Instead, I want to train my relationship in regard to the any feeling that can come up on account of anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, there will be no more problems for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if any feeling whatsoever can be rightly contained, not acted out of, it doesn't matter if it's the previous karma, other people or circumstances inflicting it upon you, you will be untouched.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the sole reason you were concerned with rationalization to begin with, is because you were touched by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, see all three feelings as impermanent?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, obviously.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fundamentally, you would be surmounting the whole domain of feelings and there would be nothing felt, as the sutra says, for an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, no arising, arisen feeling can touch him, touch the citta.
[SPEAKER_01]: I never thought about that sutta in that progressive way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, with the three feelings, see it as painful, as a dark... Well, relatively progressive way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, it's like... Circular.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm saying that these facets, they can be developed, will become
[SPEAKER_02]: More and more apparent, more easily accessible, as you start to develop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, yes, you would see there is like a progression, but it's really practice of the same principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you train in regard to the, say, say no to the core sensuality and restraining yourself and enduring the feelings that come on account of it, you are training in regard to all the feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: You won't be able to see the subtlety of the neutral feeling and right attitude, but it's already included in their development and it will lead to revelation of those other facets that you've been carrying
[SPEAKER_02]: through practicing rightly on this course level, to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in that sense, yes, because there will be more clearer facets revealed later on, facets, that's like, in that sense, it's progressive, kind of progressing practice, but it's not like one leads to two and three.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, by doing one, you are carrying two and three, and then two becomes apparent.
[SPEAKER_02]: By doing one and two, you're carrying three, and then one, two, three become apparent.
[SPEAKER_02]: By doing three, you're carrying one and two.
[SPEAKER_02]: And obviously, like, any principle of right sati, say, correctly practiced recollection of the right context, is the principle of training the animal rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, whether you're recollecting, oh, what's... what's the current... what's my current mood?
[SPEAKER_02]: What's my current... what's the current state of the animal?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it elated, depressed?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or whether you're asking yourself, what's the current enduring feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: You're basically addressing the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why force satipaṭṭhāna leads to the one-way purification of being from all the asuras.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, you know, sometimes, like, asking about the animal, thinking about the animal might just become too abstract or just, like, flat.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there is a currently enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: So how about you reveal that through your recollection?
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, not for the sake of
[SPEAKER_02]: Finding an answer or some revelation behind it, but for the sake of uncovering it, for as long as it's there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you uncover it, as we said before, through right questioning, whereby it's discerned as a thing that's already part of your situation, not as a thing that you are directly attending and merging and working with or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just want to, like, recall it without directly attending to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how am I currently feeling while I'm sitting here, doing, talking?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what you want to know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the currently enduring feeling while I continue sitting in seclusion, walking, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: And see how long, how far, how clearly can you see it indirectly, enduring, while being felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: How subtly can you perceive, how far can you see it, without moving your eyes to look for it?
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's kind of the point of the training, because for as long as your understanding
[SPEAKER_02]: and clear-seeing depend on your attention, means they're conditioned, which means when your attention changes, your wisdom goes away with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if now you're seeing things without looking at them, and can see things without needing to attend to them directly, they're always there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever you attend, whatever distracts, whatever sense comes up, occupies your mind, the framework will remain unchanged.
[SPEAKER_02]: The truth will remain the same, to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there was that... what was it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Terra Terrigata, I think.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it was that nun, that used to be like a courtesan, or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there's this whole, like, lots of verses, like, I don't know, ten, maybe more, kind of like a long poem, that ends, every section ends, but the... the... well, actually, I remember it in Serbian.
[SPEAKER_01]: How was it in English?
[SPEAKER_02]: Kind of something, like, poetically equivalent of, but the face of truth hasn't changed.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how every kind of refrain would end.
[SPEAKER_02]: And before that, she would describe how, basically, because she's like 80 years old now, everything changed.
[SPEAKER_02]: She used to have the beautiful hair, seduce people.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, it's like wrinkled, grey, falling off.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the truth remained the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: From back then, when she understood the dhamma, everything else that deteriorated, came, went, all of that, the truth, the framework, the recognition, the understanding of that, was not dependent on any of those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: On any of those activities, any of those engagements, any of those actions or, say, conditioned kind of being held up by your determination or interest and so on, the truth remain unaffected by that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as these changes occurred, the truth remained unchanged.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, her mind hasn't changed because it's been tamed and understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Independent of whether you're looking at it directly, whether your attention, whether with cues, whether with prompts, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: The internal eye has been trained sufficiently enough to see it to a sufficient extent whereby you would see it without looking at it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why dhamma is referred to as the internal eye that begins with sotāpati.
[SPEAKER_02]: Eye like... Yeah, internal eye.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the eye that sees.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not the actual eye that sees.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, Saṃsāra Smrti touches mano, i.e.
[SPEAKER_02]: attention, manasikāra, literally, are things bound with the directionality of the six senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: The dhamma, i.e.
[SPEAKER_02]: is independent of all the six senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it sees without looking through eyes, nose,
[SPEAKER_02]: Including your manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: It sees without manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't need manasikāra to see things.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't need things to be attended in order to be recognized, discerned, revealed, known, understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the yoniso part of manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now we're getting technical.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the note A. Yeah, the note A of A. Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's why, again, I'm just so vehemently and consistently against any method.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because any method is bound, cannot not be connected with ways of attending and doing and fabricating.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like it's completely taking you the other way.
[SPEAKER_02]: The more you think that's what the dhamma is, the further away from the dhamma you travel.
[SPEAKER_02]: And same.
[SPEAKER_02]: Management versus uprooting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, the same principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: If your view is about uprooting, well, you'll never go too far, even when you get caught in management or attending and shifting.
[SPEAKER_02]: But uprooting should be independent of all these acts, all these saṅkharas, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Asankatadhamma, the undetermined, the unattended, the unmanif... the unborn, the unmanifested, you know, the mystified suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's exactly what it means.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seen without a need for a direct look.
[SPEAKER_02]: And because there is such a thing that can be seen without looking, that's why nibbāna and the holy life is possible, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it weren't, unborn, unmanifested, and this and that, the whole life wouldn't be possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: So if there would be no thing that you could see without looking through six senses, then, yes, freedom from suffering would not be possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: But because there is such a thing,
[SPEAKER_02]: That you don't need six senses to see and discern and cultivate and understand and develop, then freedom from suffering is possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: But obviously, it's a lot more nice to regard it as a mystical entity of the unborn, the unmanifested, the truth, the hidden truth behind the reality of appearances and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, no, it's simply the not A of A.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing to the indirect extent, without making it into either A or B, seeing the middle way between A and B, the middle ground, without denying A completely, till it becomes another thing, or without distracting yourself away from it, till it becomes another thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you're closer to the non-eh, not-eh, you're closer to the unborn, unmanifested, you're closer to nibbāna, by training in virtue, by guarding of the sense doors, by not trying to get rid of the unpleasant things at all, by any means necessary, you are actually... you are actually uncovering
[SPEAKER_02]: That middle ground that you can eventually understand and discern without a need of looking at it directly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you do, it's not that thing anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Although on paper, oh, it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That I'm looking at, the fact that you're looking at directly, it's not the peripheral phenomenon that you need to discern.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not-a would be another word for peripheral.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, not-a would be an empty village or everything else we talked about, that the suttas describe the sense bases.
[SPEAKER_02]: They do not appear directly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it is real as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's to say, like, questioning, like, what is a currently enduring feeling, but you don't want to be directly looking at it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to learn and develop that ability to see it indirectly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, I'm, as I said, because it's there in that indirect manner.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your body is there in an indirect manner.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your feelings are there in an indirect manner.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your citta is there in an indirect manner.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those are the only means you can access them correctly.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're thinking you're doing kāyā-sati correctly by attending to it through your sensations, that's not the kāyā.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not the internal body.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not what the body is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's like your ideas and perceptions, secondary perceptions of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, body, feelings, citta, and the dhammas, the thoughts, as a phenomenon present in themselves, those things can only be known, discerned, fully understood, contemplated indirectly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only dhamma eye can see them correctly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, they won't be those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, say you discern a unpleasant feeling peripherally, but you don't fall into a trap of acting out, rationalizing it, or trying to, like, really attend to it directly, so to solve it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You leave it peripheral, but you don't completely ignore it either.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's that development of
[SPEAKER_02]: Of the dhamma, even if you don't necessarily still recognize it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And see, like, it's impossible that somebody would do this by chance.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's impossible that somebody would, for no... without any external instruction or somebody telling them and insisting that, no, no, you've got to stay on that level.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't make it into a new thing, but don't completely ignore it either.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unless somebody has learned enough to actually start gauging that balance through that external help, nobody will ever do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, say, you start, you ask yourself, how am I feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I feel a bit unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now I look at that feeling directly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I'm feeling unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: In my mind, it's the same feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: And in a way, it is the same feeling, but it's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is a difference between whether that same feeling is seen peripherally or is attended directly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that difference is not something you can see for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you see that for yourself, without external guidance, you'll become samasambuddha.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the external guidance outlines that for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: The training, they will eventually reveal the distinction between the seemingly same thing being actually seen indirectly, it's one thing, or directly, it's another thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the fundamental difference between internal and external in the suttas, including satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing indirectly, seeing peripherally, without making it into a directly attended thing, is what the domain of internal is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing it directly, directly attending to it, is what the domain of external is.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you fully train in regard to domain internal, in regard to the domain of the internal, then internal and external will become clear.
[SPEAKER_02]: They won't be conflated, they won't be confused.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the more you train in regard to the domain of the internal, for what it is, you realize it's kind of ceasing to be mine, ceasing to be internal.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why for an arahant, it's just things left there, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: He can still recognize them between, like, externally external and slightly less external.
[SPEAKER_02]: But fundamental, because the internal dimension, the peripheral, not being seen, not being developed, that's where the sense of atta is, that's where appropriation is, that's where the āsavas are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything is in that level that's neither here nor there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Neither quite in the level of A, nor quite on the level of B.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always in relation to things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why it's compared to a fire in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, it takes up the fuel, but it's not the fuel.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, upādāna, it's not the five aggregates, cannot be found in any of the five aggregates, whichever way you attend them, but it does not exist anywhere apart from them.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's in relation to them.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the not A of the A of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: A, B, C, D. And it remains not seen, because all people can see is A, B, C, D, E, F, G, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: They don't look for the relationship that's half revealed when they attend A.
[SPEAKER_02]: For relationship, that's half revealed when they attend to the bee, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, currently, enduring feeling is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing it like that, indirectly, is... Well, you could even regard it, it's like a... it's one feeling, one type.
[SPEAKER_02]: Directly attending to it, although it looks the same, feels the same, it's a different thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So now, if you directly attend to that feeling, you need to discern the peripheral to that newly directly attended feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to learn how to see it, feel it peripherally, without directly attending to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's when Yanagiri was talking about two points of view at once.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or when you speak about being simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's not like that you're denying the external, the directly attended thing, when you're discerning the peripheral.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you're just revealing both at the same time.
[SPEAKER_02]: But again, peripheral is always indirect, and that's how you need to train it, and train yourself in seeing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any tendency to make it a direct thing that you can now rationalize, think about, proliferate further,
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you gotta restrain it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't completely stop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you need to recognize that when you catch yourself in doing it, instead of denying it and, oh, let me go back to the beginning.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Discern the peripheral in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I was thinking, like, the... what you said, like, and basically the whole... like, especially, like, in the beginning, it's all about...
[SPEAKER_01]: Not really changing the direction, but undoing the just tendency of always directly attending, and you're kind of undirecting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, undoing the tendency of directly attending only to the extent necessary to reveal the implicit peripheral of whatever is directly attended.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not like to completely... because you can't.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't not have attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'll not be attending to something.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's why, again, the whole virtue and sense restraint, it's like... well, it's obviously not negotiable, but it's like part of the training, because that's how you begin.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the virtuous things, non-desire, wholesome things, are the things
[SPEAKER_02]: That, yes, you're still fully, directly attending without any recognition of the implicit, simultaneously enduring, indirect, peripheral determined by it, but they carry the possibility to see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The unwholesome things, as I said before, they remove that possibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're too far down the line towards the perversion of the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: That anything peripheral you're discerning will be tainted by it, won't be the peripheral.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, as a matter of fact, you're closer to the rightly discerning nibbānas simply through guarding your sense doors, even without any knowledge or understanding yet.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, whether you're sitting, walking, talking, eating, working,
[SPEAKER_02]: Corner of your eye, back of your mind, to that extent at the back of your mind, don't stop in order to really dig in there, because you won't be there you're digging.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just discern what is a currently enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's the currently enduring flavor of that situation?
[SPEAKER_02]: What's the currently enduring body posture?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on that level.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not stopping everything to directly attend the fact that I'm seated.
No.
[SPEAKER_02]: I already know that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Uncover that knowledge without making it into a new directly attended thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And let it endure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Protect it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's already taming the animal, taming the citta.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you do that long enough, you won't have to
[SPEAKER_02]: Be peripherally discerning your enduring feeling, or mood, or body posture to reveal the citta, you could just peripherally discern the citta.
[SPEAKER_02]: You would have seen enough signs of the mind to see the mind for what it is, which is an always indirect thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's invisible in the beginning for people.
[SPEAKER_02]: If they were not virtuous, celibate, withdrawn from sensuality, withdrawn from the company of lust, aversion, distraction, dwelling in seclusion, seeing the signs of the mind, it's not possible, as the Sutta says.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're still too close.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's more like you have... you still do not possess
[SPEAKER_02]: The capable lens that can focus on the right level between here and infinity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Focus on the right level between here and infinity.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because you know, like, the lens.
[SPEAKER_02]: You could, like, focus close up or go into infinity.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's nothing in between.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, imagine just, like, it's either focus here or there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stuff in between exists, but it's all blur.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can't be seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, training in virtue, training in restraint, training in the precept, it's basically training how to discern that which is in between, that which is, as I said, always indirect, always peripheral, always there, felt, enduring in a certain situation, without making it into a thing that I'm preoccupied with and directly kind of engaging with or attending it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why this self-questioning and recollection in that manner, that's basically the only method that you could take, because it's not really a method.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not something you can just mindlessly do or repeat.
[SPEAKER_02]: But through questioning, you kind of hint at that without seeking necessarily, okay, this is what it is, the answer or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just like, how am I feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's not like finding the right answer to the question.
[SPEAKER_02]: There isn't one.
[SPEAKER_02]: The question is, how am I feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: What am I doing?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is my current body posture?
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, you don't need to stop sitting, talking, in order to find the answer that you were sitting and talking.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's already seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: Leave it on that level and discern it and curb the tendency to... or let me make it into a more palpable thing that I can work with.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's you falling into the trap of over-attending it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the right tuning and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Too much effort, too little effort.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the current enduring mood?
[SPEAKER_02]: Just the overall.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you feel up or down?
[SPEAKER_02]: Heavy or light?
[SPEAKER_02]: Inspired or depressed?
[SPEAKER_02]: You already know that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even the most asutava person, and then read no suttas or anything, would be able to give you an answer to this.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you ask them to explain it, they would fall into some
[SPEAKER_02]: External psychologization, rationalization, through whatever kind of concoction of modern science, slash, medicine, views, ideas of consciousness, or whatever, to explain it, it's going to be nonsense, obviously.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, first and foremost, they will tell you how they feel.
[SPEAKER_02]: They'll tell you what mood they're in.
[SPEAKER_02]: They'll just won't be able to stay on that phenomenological level without making it into something that it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when we ask those questions, it's more about the... when you say, as well, let the question endure, like, don't jump for an answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're not looking for an answer, you're looking for uncovering what's already there, which, as I said, accidentally, is the right answer, but not if you answer it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's, in a way, it's as well getting to know the process of how you attempt to answer it,
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's more like about curbing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, like, because you could see how people would fall into then... well, they wouldn't be able to stay on that level.
[SPEAKER_02]: They would either be not asking the question...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just everything is like self-evident, whatever I can observe and measure, which is, you know, the vast majority of, say, commentarially oriented Buddhists, because often you hear that, like, oh, modern science and Buddhism are saying the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything is measurable, predefined, their factors, their results, and it's all like, you know, moment A leads to moment B, the moment C. So, that's like one extreme, in terms of the views, but then you have another extreme, where you would ask the question, but then mystify the question.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, there is no answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, well, no, you've got to find a middle ground.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you do... you are seeking the answer, just not on your own terms.
[SPEAKER_02]: But see, when you tell people, well, you can't just answer it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you fall into a trap of that materialist view, the commentarial view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then they go the other way and then they say, well, there's no answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you just ask the question and whatever space opens up becomes their answer, becomes overly attended thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: They think it's a non-answer because they abstain from the answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because often you hear that from, kind of, Advaita Buddhists, how I call them.
[SPEAKER_02]: They would often tend to, like, you know, they would say things like, don't hold to fixed views.
[SPEAKER_02]: And completely oblivious to the fact that that is their fixed view.
[SPEAKER_02]: That they very much hold on to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or it's like, abstain from any judgment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, ease your form of judgment.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not as easy as to just abstain from answering to find that middle ground.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Abstaining from answering will become your form of answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, again, you're overly attending it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't know how not to make it into a thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why it's like, yes, it's correct.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ask a question.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't seek an answer, but it doesn't mean, oh, and be open to whatever universe reveals to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: You do need to find the answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just can't be you who is providing the answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, ask the question looking for an answer, but abstain from answering it, but remain looking for an answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you get the right balance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't abandon the implication of the question.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is an answer there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to discern it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you dismiss it and become like a universe worshiping mystic, the peripheral remains hidden, remains covered, the middle ground, middle way remains obscured.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you just answer it because, you know, quote the Abhidhamma that answers everything,
[SPEAKER_02]: As as moving systems and parts, everything fits and explains.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, you obscured the fact that there is an answer that wasn't on your own terms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you stated the right thing, but you stated it as an answer, as something that you directly attended, it's not that peripheral thing that's being felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that dimension remains obscured for as long as you're rushing in with your answers.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's like... it's incomprehensible.
[SPEAKER_02]: For people that approach the suttas with that kind of, as I said, scientific... everything is explainable.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the five factors and the four this... the seven steps lead to the eight and three and two.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, people back in the day used that simply to remember, to help, like, cultivate the transmission memory.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now, today, that became just like a... like a factual listings.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, from that point of view, well, there is nothing else to do in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just gotta learn and internalize the ideas of these lists, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything... because they're there to explain, not to lead onwards, as the suttas would say.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if information is not leading you onwards to see it for yourself, it's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if it's the right thing repeated on the paper,
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's that thing that Nenāvera said when that logician, I think, some mathematician-logician, was presented the suttas, and he read it, and he's like, oh, well, this is mere tautology.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because he couldn't see that there's anything to develop, because it's... he approached it as a statement of facts.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when, you know, the Buddha says, the one who doesn't act, you know, out of their desire, the desire diminishes.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, oh, yeah, well, that's just a statement of facts.
[SPEAKER_02]: I already know that.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, I already have an information.
[SPEAKER_02]: But one thing is to have an information, another thing is to recognize... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: There has to be training implicit in this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Behavior that... that actually guides in that direction whereby these things are seen, and then the dimension becomes... the dimension of the indirect feeling, the indirect body and so on, become revealed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Without it, as I said, you will be thinking it, and you will be thinking that you are thinking it, but it won't be it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The middle way won't exist for as long as that the signs of the mind, the indirect, is not seen to the sufficient extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why, again, the entire Noble Eightfold Path rests upon the Right View, the Noble View, the Noble Internal Dhamma Eye.
[SPEAKER_02]: Without it, there is no Noble Eightfold Path, even if you make perfect sense out of it and everything fits.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not seeing it for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, seeing that indirect, without directly looking at it, is what it means, seeing things for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because nobody can come in between that.
[SPEAKER_02]: No circumstance, no chance, no sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not dependent on the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just between you and your point of view, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even Mara can come in between that, as the suttas tell us.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mystical side and the scientific... obviously, they're both... both Bs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are they... would you say that is a kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: All-encompassing dichotomy of, like... Yeah, it's like all of the views, whatever permutations of the individual combinations, would boil down to these two, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either you'll be leaning on the explanatory side, or on the side that dismisses the implication of the question, and just starts to glorify the question in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you said that, like, it wasn't the context of pleasant, unpleasant, a neutral feeling, and you were saying that the neutral feeling is more, quote-unquote, in the peripheral than the other two.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well...
[SPEAKER_02]: No, they're all peripheral whenever they're felt, but it's more like...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the subtlest to discern.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the hardest to discern correctly as a phenomenon without overdoing it or underdoing it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you said it for whatever, I thought like, yeah, how do I usually...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, what do I associate with... Like, with pleasant and painful feeling, there's usually a certain...
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, see, even the suttas describe it... they don't call it neutral.
[SPEAKER_02]: They call it neither pleasant nor unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or neither unpleasant nor pleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's the absence of the two that reveals it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you see, it's like twice as indirect, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pleasure and pain are already indirect.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, feeling is already indirect to whatever you're directly perceiving.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's already... the nature of feeling already means a different, less direct direction of your perception, to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's the absence of pleasure or pain, when you know that it's that's what's felt, that's how you discern the neutral.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's like indirectly-indirect.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the neutral feeling is...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's defined by not being neither pleasant nor unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: By absence.
[SPEAKER_02]: By absence of pleasure and pain, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Simultaneously enduring absence of pleasure and pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because the other ones had, when I thought about it, they had, they have a certain fullness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: A bit more palpable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the neutral feeling is most of the time not seen, not known, which is why it's felt unpleasantly.